Alright, today's דף daf is דף י"ד, daf Yod-Dalet, and we kick
off with the משנה mishnah on the bottom of י"ג עמוד ב'.
Yod-Gimmel Amud Bet. Let's take a look. So the previous one had
discussed what you need in terms of a לחי lechi and a
קורה. korah. Now we're discussing what the לחי lechi and the קורה
korah look like. So הקורה שאמרו, ha-korah she-amru, when they speak about
the קורה, korah, the horizontal beam, רחבה כדי לקבל אריח. rechava kidei
lekabel ariach. That's to be wide enough that it could support that
you know you could you could place an אריח, ariach, a brick
on it. מה דהוא גזי דביתא? mah de-hu gizei de-veita? אריח חצי
לבינה, ariach chatzi leveinah, brick is half of a לבינה. leveinah. A
לבינה leveinah is a tile that was three by three טפחים. tefachim.
So a brick is three טפחים tefachim long by a טפח tefach
and a half wide.
Alright. דיה לקורה שתהא רחבה טפח כדי לקבל אריח לרחבו. dai lakorah
she-tehe rechava tefach kidei lekabel ariach leracho.
It's enough that it's a טפח tefach wide so it can you
can place a brick on it widthwise. So if this is your
one and a half טפח tefach brick, if it's three by one
and a half, and this is your קורה, korah, you could put
the brick on it like this. Now there's a little overhang of
a quarter of a טפח tefach on each side. But the גמרא
Gemara is going to say that that's okay, as long as if
it's a טפח tefach and this only overhangs a quarter טפח tefach
on each side, you could plaster it in theory, you know and
put plaster there to keep it attached to the קורה. korah. So
basically from there we get the idea that the קורה korah has
to be a טפח tefach but rather than just coming straight out
and saying it, it's telling you conceptually the idea of a קורה
korah is to function as a piece of a frame of a
doorway where then you would lay a brick on top of it.
Now
now we get an idea that's not just conceptual. רחבה כדי לקבל
אריח, rechava kidei lekabel ariach, so we just said it has to
be wide enough for it to accept to be to support a
brick, but there's another criterion as well. ובריאה כדי לקבל אריח. ubri'ah
kidei lekabel ariach. It has to be strong enough that if you
put a brick on it it would be able to support. Now
interestingly it doesn't say that you could lay a row of bricks
on it. That would have to be even stronger. But at least
one brick it has to be strong enough to support. רבי יהודה
אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda makes is purely
a formalist. He doesn't care about whether in practice it can support
this. He just wants it to be the right dimensions. So רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says רחבה אף על פי שאינה בריאה. rechava af
al pi she-eina bri'ah.
If it's wide enough even if it's not strong enough. It's all
just about the dimensions, which interestingly is what we normally assume. Meaning
we've gotten used to assuming that all of these things are you
know somewhat types of like fictions or symbolic and it's all about
the dimensions and here we're actually finally getting a criteria of the
rabbis that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda disagrees with that says it actually
has to support a support a what do you call it a
brick itself. Now הייתה של קש ושל קנים, hayeta shel kash veshel
kanim,
let's say you made your קורה korah out of reeds or out
of straw or sticks so like you know the three little pigs.
So so the rabbis had said it has to be strong enough
to accept a brick. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is not making that
and this elaborates on רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position. רואין אותה כאילו
הייתה של מתכת. ro'in otah ke'ilu hayeta shel matechet. You pretend as
if it was made out of metal. So it doesn't matter you
go oh my god it's so thin and it well it's not
thin it has to be a טפח, tefach, but it's made out
of straw it would collapse. Doesn't matter for רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
In theory if that were made out of metal it would be
good enough. So it's good now. Again his position that it's all
about the dimensions and not about the actual ability to function as
a piece of a doorframe.
עקומה, akumah, let's say it was bent. רואין אותה כאילו פשוטה. ro'in
otah ke'ilu peshutah. You look at it as if it's straight. Now
that's interesting because you could say bent hides the dimensions you know
and bent wouldn't work. But again that doesn't bother him.
We'll see in the גמרא Gemara exactly some limits on the bent
idea. עגולה, agulah, let's say it is circular. רואין אותה כאילו היא
מרובעת. ro'in otah ke'ilu hi meruba'at. You look at it as if
it's rectangular. This means not obviously it's obviously running the length but
let's say it's more of a pole than it is of a
beam. So if it's a pole it's like a long cylinder, so
you couldn't lay a brick on top of a cylinder. But for
him it doesn't matter. You look at it as if it were
squared off. For רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda even the shape of it
doesn't matter as long as it is a טפח, tefach, the shape
the strength doesn't matter as long as it's a טפח tefach wide.
Now כל שיש בהיקפו שלושה טפחים יש בו רוחב טפח. kol she-yesh
beheikefo sheloshah tefachim yesh bo rochav tefach. And there's going to be
an interesting discussion in the גמרא. Gemara. Anything it's pi but it's
a very rough estimation of pi. Right, anything that is exactly we'll
discuss anything that has a circumference of three has a width of
one. Which basically means I mean I know you know what it
means but what it means for our purposes is if the circumference
is three then the width is one. Which by the way this
is a קולא kula now because since we know that pi is
actually 3.14
if you actually have a circumference of three the width is going
to be less than one and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would still
say it's okay. So even if it does not meet very often
when we talk about circles like let's say we talk about is
something an אוהל ohel if it has to be a טפח tefach
by a... A טפח. tefach. And if it's a circular one טפח
tefach wide, that's not good enough because you have to be able
to square a טפח tefach by a טפח tefach inside of it.
That's often when we're talking about a circle, we're talking about squaring
a טפח tefach by טפח tefach inside here, it's not required, because
we only make the demand in terms of one dimension. So since
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says I don't care how strong it is,
if it's cylindrical like this, if you were to cut off the
top half and you would just have a טפח tefach here, right,
that's fine, because you only need it to be a טפח tefach
wide to receive the brick. It doesn't need to be a טפח
tefach you know thick, it only needs to be a טפח tefach
wide. So as long as it's three טפחים tefachim in circumference, you
can use it because you imagine as if it were cut in
half and as if you could get the cross-section which is a
טפח tefach wide. So that is רב יהודה Rav Yehuda who does
not require that in practice it be able to receive a brick,
to put a brick on it, it's just that it has the
dimension of being a טפח tefach wide and here we find out
even at any one point. Yes?
How long does that have to be?
From one end of the מבוי mavoi to the other. So it
has to reach from one end of the מבוי mavoi to the
other. It has to be a טפח tefach wide at one point,
one point along the length, consistently along the length, but it does
not have to be a particular thickness. Yes?
So this is just for a קורה, kora, this doesn't apply for
the top of a צורת הפתח? tzurat hapetach?
Well, that's a good point. Whether this definition, sort of, requirements of
a קורה kora are consistent with that of a צורת הפתח tzurat
hapetach is interesting. You are right that the חכמים chachamim who according
to many we rule like, that a קורה kora has to actually
have the strength כדי לקבל אריח. kedei lekabel ariach. We do not
make that demand by a צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach. צורת הפתח tzurat
hapetach we use like a string. So it doesn't have to be,
it doesn't even have to be, maybe more to the point in
addition to the issue of strength, צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach the top
doesn't even have to be a טפח tefach wide. Okay? So this
is by a קורה kora which stands by itself. When you have
the entire צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, you are correct, and the top
thing has a lesser criteria. Okay, so now let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. Top of דף יא עמוד א. Daf Yud
Aleph Amud Aleph.
טפח. tefach. So it's a טפח tefach wide. You just said that
it has to be able to put a brick on it. A
brick is a טפח ומחצה tefach u'mechtza wide. טפח ומחצה בעי. tefach
u'mechtza ba'ei. You should need a טפח tefach and a half. So
the גמרא Gemara says
כיון דרחב וקבל טפח, keivan d'rachav v'kabel tefach, since it's wide enough
for a טפח tefach of the brick to go on it, אידך
חצי טפח, idach chatzi tefach, so the other half טפח tefach that
the brick is wider, משוי ליה בטינא משהו מהאי גיסא ומשהו מהאי
גיסא, mashvei lei betina mashehu mehai gisa u'mashehu mehai gisa, you basically
plaster it with plaster, a little bit on one side, a little
bit on the other side, because it hangs over a quarter of
a טפח tefach on each side,
וקיימא, v'kayma, and it will stay. So actually you could lay bricks
on top of a post that is a little bit narrower than
the width of the brick itself. אמר רבה בר רב הונא. Amar
Rabba bar Rav Huna. קורה שאמרו צריכה שתהא בריאה כדי לקבל אריח,
kora she'amru tzaricha shetehei bria kedei lekabel ariach, as we said, according
to the חכמים, chachamim, the קורה kora has to be not only
a טפח tefach wide but strong enough for the brick to go
on it, but ומעמידי קורה אינם צריכים שיהיו בריאים כדי לקבל קורה
ואריח. u'maamidei kora einam tzarichim sheyehu briim kedei lekabel kora v'ariach. The
supports of the beam do not have to be strong enough to
support the beam and the brick. So if here you've got your
beam, right, and it's let's say on a peg at the end
of the מבוי. mavoi. My thumb is the peg and okay we'll
do it this way, it's on these pegs at the end of
the מבוי. mavoi. If you were to put a brick on it,
the brick might not break the קורה. kora. The קורה kora is
strong enough for the brick. But the combined weight of the brick
and the קורה kora would break it off from its pegs, from
its supports. So he says, that doesn't matter. You're not actually putting
a brick on it, and so the question is, what is that
balance between it sort of being a
symbolizing the door frame and actually being able to function as a
door frame? So he says, okay, once it's not only wide enough
but strong enough, it doesn't matter if in practice if you were
to put the brick on, it would collapse because the supporting pegs
would collapse. Does anyone disagree? No, he's explaining the position of the
חכמים. chachamim. Okay. So it's only about requiring the beam, not about
caring about the actual supports of the beam. רב חסדא אמר. Rav
Chisda amar. רב חסדא Rav Chisda disagrees. רב חסדא Rav Chisda says
אחד זה ואחד זה צריכים שיהיו בריאים כדי לקבל קורה ואריח. echad
zeh v'echad zeh tzarichim sheyehu briim kedei lekabel kora v'ariach.
Both of them have to be able to support it putting on
the brick. So the beam has to be able to support the
brick, and the pegs have to be able to support the beam
with the brick. Again, it is interesting though, apparently it's just one
brick, you don't have to lay a whole row of bricks on
it. אמר רב ששת. Amar Rav Sheshet. הניח קורה על גבי מבוי
ופרס עליה מחצלת. hiniach kora al gabei mavoi u'paras aleha machatzelet. והגביה
מן הקרקע שלשה. v'higbia min hakarka shlosha.
Very interesting. Here is your קורה kora and you thought you were
going to be really frum. So yeah, I got a קורה, kora,
I know it's enough, but I want it to really look like
a door. So I'm going to lay a mat over my קורה
kora here like this. So now hanging in front of my מבוי
mavoi is actually almost like, you know, a curtain. It's this mat
hanging from the קורה. kora. There's only a little problem: the curtain
here, the mat, is more than three טפחים tefachim off the ground.
So it doesn't count as a wall. It would have to be
within three to say לבוד, lavud, it's like it's continuous, to count
as a wall. Now that it's more than three טפחים tefachim removed,
it's not a wall. So it's not counting as a wall, so
it doesn't do you any good. Okay, but at least use the
קורה. kora. Only a little problem now using the קורה. korah. What's
the problem using the קורה?
korah? Well, first you say it's a היכר, heker, and then it's
covered up.
It's no longer is visible. So if a קורה korah is because
of היכר, heker, you got a problem. So that's what he said.
הניח קורה אגב מבוי, Hiniach korah agabei mavoi, you have your קורה,
korah, ופרס עליה מחצלת, ufaras aleha machatzelet, and you and you spread
a mat over it, והגביה מן הקרקע שלושה, vehigbia min hakarka shlosha,
and the bottom of the mat is more than three טפחים tefachim
removed from the ground. קורה אין כאן מחיצה אין כאן, Korah ein
kan mechitzah ein kan, you neither have a קורה korah or a
מחיצה. mechitzah. קורה אין כאן דהא מכסיא, Korah ein kan deha michasya,
you don't have a קורה korah because it's covered, and this assumes
that קורה korah is משום היכר. mishum heker. That's been an ongoing
discussion, but the emphasis seemed to be that קורה korah was היכר
heker and לחי lechi was מחיצה. mechitzah. So if it doesn't have
this היכר heker issue, it doesn't count as a היכר. heker. מחיצה
אין כאן, Mechitzah ein kan, and it's not a מחיצה, mechitzah, דהוי
ליה מחיצה שהגדייים בוקעין בה. dehavei lei mechitzah shehagedayim boke'in bah. It's
a מחיצה mechitzah that kids, goats, could run underneath it. Now it's
interesting, you could have said this more formalistically: it's not a מחיצה
mechitzah because it doesn't touch the ground. The גמרא Gemara very practically
points out you can't call it a מחיצה mechitzah wall because in
practice it doesn't stop passage. As long as the goats could run
underneath it—interestingly it's defined by goats and not people—it doesn't function as
a מחיצה. mechitzah. Now why did the גמרא Gemara have to give
that additional reason? Why didn't they just say it's not touching the
ground? So there are two explanations. One is, as we're going to
see in a minute, you'll remember there's a position of רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel that actually says that לבוד lavud
is four טפחים. tefachim. So according to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel, you would think that a מחיצה mechitzah could be
removed up to four טפחים tefachim from the ground. The גמרא's Gemara
going to say in a minute, no, even though
theoretically it's connected, if in practice the goats run underneath it, even
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel would say it's no
good. So even according to him it has to be within three
טפחים. tefachim. Another reason we have to say that is, we're going
to see later, and we see in סוכות Sukkos as well, that
sometimes you have this idea that the מחיצה mechitzah extends upward or
extends downward, like your מחיצה, mechitzah, your wall of your סוכה Sukkah
doesn't have to hit the סכך. sechach. If your wall is ten
טפחים tefachim here on your סכך sechach is up here, you imagine
it as if the wall goes straight up and is in contact
with the סכך. sechach. Okay, so if you're and sometimes we say
that a wall extends magically downward as well. But once you point
out the problem about the goats going underneath it, that in practice
it doesn't stop passage, that practical problem, you know, contradiction, could prevent
us saying in הלכה, halachic, you know, imagination that the wall goes
down. It's harder to say the wall goes down than the wall
goes up, because wall goes up, at least it's functioning practically to
block passage at nearest to the ground. But to have it high
and imagine it going down, that's more of a challenge because of
this idea of the goats going through it. So that's what the
גמרא Gemara says here. The covering up of the קורה korah removes
its function as a קורה, korah, and because it's not within three
of the ground, it doesn't function as a מחיצה, mechitzah, so you
just made things worse. A perfect example of כל המוסיף גורע. kol
hamosif goreia. Alright, so now we continue.
תנו רבנן. Tanu rabbanan. קורה היוצאה מכותל זה ואינה נוגעת בכותל זה.
Korah hayotzei mikotel zeh ve’eina noga’at bekotel zeh. You have a beam
that goes from one wall and doesn't reach the end of the
other wall. Right, this is the problem: how long does it have
to be? We know it has to be a טפח tefach wide,
it doesn't have to be any particular thickness except according to חכמים
chachamim just in practice being able to be able to support a
brick. How about how long it has to be? So it has
to go from one wall to the next. So if it goes
from one wall and doesn't reach the next, וכן שתי קורות אחת
יוצאה מכותל זה ואחת יוצאה מכותל זה ואינן נוגעות זו בזו, vechen
shetei korot, achat yotzei mikotel zeh ve’achat yotzei mikotel zeh, ve’einan nog’ot
zo bezo, or you have two beams, one's coming from one wall,
the other from the other, but they don't actually meet in the
middle. Sort of like when they try—when they made the channel. You
know with this, right? They also did this by חזקיהו's Chizkiyahu tunnel.
Right, I mean it's amazing how they were able to do it
then. You know, but they actually, they split the time in half
by one team starting in England and one starting in France, and
they actually met in the middle. And they had to be like
perfect.
They were off by about this much? They were? Okay, so amazing
how well...
Right, but the amazing thing is they did it in חזקיהו's Chizkiyahu
tunnel as well, which was like three thousand years ago, without any,
without the kind of... I mean ממש mamash like a נס נפלא.
nes nifla. So anyway, so you have that. You have these two
beams coming and they don't yet meet yet in the middle. Okay,
does that count?
פחות משלושה
אין צריך להביא קורה אחרת. Pachot mishlosha ein tzarich lehavi korah acheret.
If the beams are within three טפחים tefachim of one another, you
know, then you don't have to bring another beam. Now we're going
to assume they're perfectly in line, there's just a gap of three
טפחים. tefachim. Okay, we'll talk about what if they're not in line.
So if there's a gap of less than three טפחים tefachim or
if there's three טפחים tefachim between the beam and the adjoining wall,
then you don't need another beam. You're fine. Within three טפחים tefachim
is considered connected. שלושה צריך להביא קורה אחרת. Shlosha tzarich lehavi korah
acheret. Three or more טפחים, tefachim, you have to fill that gap.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says, פחות מארבעה אין צריך להביא
קורה אחרת. pachot me'arba'ah ein tzarich lehavi korah acheret. No, the definition
of לבוד lavud is not three, but it's four. So less than
four you don't need another beam, it's considered connected. ארבעה צריך להביא
קורה אחרת. Arba'ah tzarich lehavi korah acheret. Four or more טפחים, tefachim,
you have to bring another beam.
Does לבוד lavud work horizontally with the with the?
Yeah, לבוד lavud works horizontally.
No, the four and not
oh, okay, so I I I I gave you that. as ahead.
So the גמרא's Gemara going to say that, right? You figured that
out from what I said.
Okay. וכן v'chein similarly, שתי קורות המתאימות, shtei koros hamas'imos, לא בזו
כדי לקבל אריח ולא בזו כדי לקבל אריח. lo bizo k'dei l'kabel
ariach v'lo bizo k'dei l'kabel ariach. Now this isn't exactly a similarly,
it's similar in that it's a similar scenario, but the same הלכה
halakha doesn't apply. You've got two beams, and in each beam, I
don't know where I should have, oh, there's another marker. Okay, so
this is going to be a good brick. All right, so you've
got as opposed to the beams going like this and not reaching
in the middle, they're going parallel. Okay, they're going like this. The
only thing, so why do you need two? Because neither of them
is a טפח tefach wide. So can you use לבוד lavud to
make it an imaginary טפח? tefach? Now the problem is, is that
the more you emphasize the idea of a טפח tefach is in
practice, it could support a brick, then maybe it wouldn't go just
by the classic לבוד lavud definitions. And the Rabbis we know as
opposed to Rabbi Yehuda in practice needs it to support a brick.
So let's take a look.
וכן שתי קורות המתאימות, v'chein shtei koros hamas'imos, two beams that are
running parallel. לא בזו כדי לקבל אריח ולא בזו כדי לקבל אריח.
lo bizo k'dei l'kabel ariach v'lo bizo k'dei l'kabel ariach. This one
isn't wide enough, isn't a טפח tefach wide to get a
brick, and that one isn't. אם מקבלות אריח לרחבו טפח, im m'kablos
ariach l'rachbo tefach, if they could support an אריח ariach by its
width, a טפח tefach wide, אין צריך להביא קורה אחרת, ein tzarich
l'havi kora acheres, you don't need another beam. ואם לאו צריך להביא
קורה אחרת, v'im lav tzarich l'havi kora acheres, and if not you
need another beam. Now what does that mean? It means if these
are, let's say, within three טפחים, tefachim, who the heck cares if
they're within three טפחים? tefachim? If you tried to put a brick
down it would fall through. But if they're within a טפח tefach
of one another, like then, I only have two hands here, but
you get the idea. If they're within a טפח tefach of one
another and you put the brick on, it would successfully support the
brick. Picture... okay, good, there's the picture. So you get the idea.
So anyway, you don't need... three טפחים tefachim won't work. You need
them to be within a טפח tefach of one another. Now one
does wonder why you need them to be within a טפח. tefach.
Since we said the brick was a טפח tefach and a half,
wouldn't it be enough that they were within a טפח tefach and
a half of one another? Right? So I don't really know the
answer to that, but I'm assuming that if the gap is too
much, if they're too much at the edge, it won't be a
good support. You know, so the gap has to be less than
a טפח, tefach, so at least some of the quarter טפח tefach
goes onto the beam.
But the thing is, you still need to be a טפח, tefach,
because you can think if the brick is straddling two, there don't
need to be half a טפח. tefach.
Right, well, that's the thing. It does seem to be that you
do not...
that it could be more... what... meaning it seems like if this
is, if the gap is a טפח, tefach, is less than a
טפח, tefach, that's good. So the entire width...
No, what I'm saying is, our criteria was that these beams need
to be a טפח tefach wide, right? But what I'm saying is,
if they're spaced, I could even see each of them only being
a quarter of a טפח. tefach.
Yes, each beam could be very thin. Oh, okay. Yeah, as long
as in practice, right, the gap is no more than a טפח,
tefach, and then you could support it between the two.
Wait, was there... I'm misunderstanding something, but the issue about the plaster...
Yeah,
that makes up the טפח... tefach... the half...
The half, right. Well, that supports the brick. We don't actually, I
don't think we're actually saying the plaster has to actually increase the
thickness to a טפח tefach and a half. It has to just
support the brick.
Right, but if you have the support under the plaster, theoretically, it
wouldn't hold the brick. Maybe that's why it has to be within
a טפח. tefach. If you...
one more time? If you...
what's the question?
The only question I have is, why don't you allow, if these
are your two parallel beams, why don't you allow there to be,
you know, 1.4 between them, and then you could still support the
1.5 טפח tefach brick? So I think the answer is, right, is
that that's not very stable. That you need there to be one
טפח tefach with them, so the actual, you know, brick gets at
least like a quarter of a טפח tefach onto each beam, it's
more stable. So therefore we can only allow a טפח tefach between
the two. That's the way I'm understanding why we only allow a
טפח, tefach, even though the actual brick is a טפח tefach and
a half. Yes, you need the plaster to help support it, but
I just think that if it's too far away, it won't be
stable. Okay, so it has to be a טפח. tefach. We do
not go three טפחים. tefachim. One does wonder what Rabbi Yehuda would
say, who doesn't care about practical its ability to support a brick
at all. So it says, where are we? רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, אם מקבלת אריח לארכו שלושה, im
m'kabales ariach l'archo shlosha, אין צריך להביא קורה אחרת. ein tzarich l'havi
kora acheres. He says no, since when do
you have
to do it width-wise? I'll be more lenient here. I agree that
you don't go by לבוד. lavud. If I went by לבוד, lavud,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel's לבוד lavud is four טפחים, tefachim, but why
not turn the bricks in the other direction? So even if they're
up to three טפחים tefachim separate, you don't need another קורה. kora.
ואם לאו צריך להביא קורה אחרת, v'im lav tzarich l'havi kora acheres,
if not you do. Which makes it sound, since for him, he's
positioning the brick, or actually I have the brick here drawn width-wise.
So since the brick is three טפחים tefachim wide and he's positioning
it length-wise, and he says only if you go by three טפחים
tefachim because you can just orient the brick that way. It sounds
like when we're measuring, we're measuring actually the outer edges of the
קורה, kora, not the gap between it. So if that's true according
to the חכמים chachamim as well, when they were describing a brick
in this direction, and they said one and a half, one, it
sounds like they're describing the from the outer edges. Again, which is
funny, which means that they still actually demand that it has the
overhang. Why they would demand that it has the overhang I don't...
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues. I mean to allow for the
overhang. Why you would demand the overhang is not clear. Okay, anyway
now the גמרא Gemara continues. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר. Rabbi Yose
b'Rabbi Yehuda omer. Did I skip a line? ואי לאו צריך לאתויי
קורה אחת, Ve'im lav tzarich le'atuvei kora achas, היו אחת למעלה ואחת
למטה. Hayu achas lemala ve'achas lemata.
So we did side by side and we did not reaching. Let's
say they're on different heights, okay?
So you have it, yes, but again, they don't go the entire
length. This one goes half the length, this one goes half the
length, but they're at different heights. So even if they're within three
טפחים, tefachim, you don't have a continuous bar. So what's the story?
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר רואין את העליונה כאילו היא למטה והתחתונה
כאילו היא למעלה. Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda omer ro'in es ha'elyona k'ilu
hi lemata vehatachtona k'ilu hi lemala. You look at the higher one
as if it's
lower down, or the lower and, but really it's enough that you
say or, or the lower one as if it's higher up. You're
able to move along the vertical plane. And there, and if they
would connect, you're fine. ובלבד שלא תהא עליונה למעלה מכף אמה ותחתונה
למטה מעשרה. U'bilvad shelo tehei eliyona lemala m'kaf ama vetachtona lemata m'asara.
But each beam by itself has to be in a good position.
If the top one is higher than twenty אמות amos or the
bottom one is less than ten טפחים, tefachim, then that beam is
no good. But if each beam by itself is in a good
position and you're allowed to move them along the vertical plane to
imagine as if they were evened up, which is interesting. Why is
that more lenient? Before we needed three טפחים tefachim to connect, or
we needed it to be practically to support the אריח, ariach, but
here where it's just an issue of not connecting to the wall
and not supporting the brick, but just getting them on the same
plane, we're more able to move. This does connect to this idea
that sometimes by walls we do say you extend upward or you
extend downward. So here it's not a wall, it's a קורה, kora,
but to some degree we're doing that.
You would do that? You know, within like nineteen
אמות amos of each other? It doesn't seem like much of a...
I know, it's pretty bizarre. I would totally agree that if they're
that far apart... Anyway the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר אביי רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה סבר
לה כאבוה בחדא ופליג עליה
בחדא. Amar Abaye Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda savar lah ke'avuh bechada ufalig
aleh bechada. סבר לה כאבוה בחדא, Savar lah ke'avuh bechada, סבר לה
כאבוה, savar lah ke'avuh, סבר לה כאבוה בחדא דאית ליה רואין. savar
lah ke'avuh bechada de'is leh ro'in.
He holds like his father in
one, that he has "we see". What does this mean? Remember רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said it doesn't practically have to be able to
support a brick. That now that's understandable, 'cause if you've got one
like this, it's not practically supporting a brick. So the father says
you imagine as if. Now where did he say that? He says,
well, even if it's made out of straw, you imagine as if
it's made out of metal. So, which is an interesting position, 'cause
you could have said, I don't need to imagine, I don't need
it to support a brick, I just need it to be a
טפח tefach wide. You know, when you sort of reject the rabbis
say it has to support a brick, and you reject it. There
are two possibilities: you completely reject the criteria, it doesn't have to
support a brick, or you could say I agree with the criteria,
but I'll pretend it meets the criteria satisfied. I'll look at something
like straw as if it's made out of metal. Now it's a
funny why you would adopt that position. I mean it makes somewhat
sense because you still want it to function conceptually as a piece
of a doorframe. Anyway so that's how the גמרא Gemara explains it.
What that is a help is if you are willing to say
I imagine as if, then if you've got them on different planes,
you could say, oh, well, I'll imagine as if they're connected. Once
we're sort of just making it up, we're imagining, we'll imagine that
way as well. So we hold like his father that he allows
you to do that. And of course it works 'cause it doesn't
practically have to be able to support a brick, so you could
imagine as if they're on the same plane.
ופליג עליה בחדא, Upalig aleh bechada, דאילו רבי יהודה סבר למעלה מכף.
de'ilu Rabbi Yehuda savar lemala m'kaf. If you remember the very first
משנה, mishna, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you can have it higher
than twenty אמה. ama. ורבי יוסי ברבי יהודה סבר, Ve'Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi
Yehuda savar, but he, the son, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose
b'Rabbi Yehuda holds, בתוך כף אין למעלה מכף לא. betoch kaf in
lemala m'kaf lo. Only within twenty, because he said the beam has
to be within twenty.
So this discussion was very interesting
in clarifying a couple of things. Number one is you can say
לבוד, lavud, it has to reach the opposite wall but you can
say לבוד, lavud, debate of three or four טפחים, tefachim, we of
course rule three. Number two, when they're parallel, then it's not just
a question of saying לבוד, lavud, but in practice, according to the
חכמים, chachamim, not רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it has to be able
to take the brick, so they have to be closer to one
another if they're in parallel. And if they're on different planes, the
חכמים chachamim presumably would totally reject that. Maybe they would accept it
within three טפחים, tefachim, probably not though, because if they're on different
planes, there's no way it can support a brick. But רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda following his father who says we
don't need it to support a brick, or you imagine as if
it does, so then he would say even on separate planes, you
imagine as if they are on the same plane and therefore it
works. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues. רבי יהודה אומר רחב אף
פי שאינו בריא. Rabbi Yehuda omer rachav af pi she'eino bari. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it could be wide even if it is
not strong. That's what we just said. רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehudah does
not need in practice to be able to support the brick. So
the גמרא Gemara
says: מתני ליה רב יהודה—this matnei leih Rav Yehudah is רב יהודה,
Rav Yehudah, not רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehudah. So רב יהודה Rav Yehudah
taught this משנה mishnah to חייא בר רב, Chiya bar Rav, חייא
Chiya the son of רב, Rav, קמיה דרב kamei de-Rav in the
front of רב. Rav. רחבה אף על פי שאינה בריאה—that rechava af
pi she-einah bri'ah not that that like our משנה mishnah says, wide
even though it's not strong enough. That's the position of רבי יהודה.
Rebbe Yehudah. אמר ליה—so amar leih רב Rav said to him: אתנייה
רחבה ובריאה. atni'ei rechava u-vri'ah. No, no, no, that's not what it
should read. It should read wide and strong. Now, of course, if,
first of all, if you remember, רב Rav corrected before, you know,
in a מחמיר machmir way, that our first משנה mishnah said that
if you have a צורת הפתח tzurat ha-petach it can be wider
than ten אמות. amot. And when חייא בר רב Chiya bar Rav
was—and when who is—I think it was the same רב יהודה. Rav
Yehudah. I think it was רב יהודה. Rav Yehudah. I think it
was the same person, which was רב יהודה, Rav Yehudah, was teaching
חייא, Chiya, רב's Rav son, רב Rav said, "No, no, don't say
if it's a צורת הפתח tzurat ha-petach it doesn't have to be
smaller. Say even with a צורת הפתח tzurat ha-petach you still have
to make it less than ten." So he changed the גרסא, girsa,
or he had a different גרסא girsa of the משנה, mishnah, which
was more strict. So here he's saying where רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehudah
says it's enough that it's thick, it's enough that it's wide even
though it's not strong, no, no, no, change the text. You should
say it has to be wide and strong. Now the problem is,
is that's exactly the position of the חכמים. Chachamim. So what does
he think the debate is between רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehudah and the
חכמים? Chachamim? חכמים Chachamim say wide and strong, רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehudah
says wide and strong the way he edited it. So תוספות Tosafot
actually says a very ingenious פשט. pshat.
He describes a position. He was just saying the הלכה. halakhah.
Oh, so that's one idea. Maybe he's just paskin-ing, but it doesn't
sound that way. It sounds like he's changing the text of the
משנה mishnah or correcting the text. So תוספות Tosafot says he's not
correcting רבי יהודה's Rebbe Yehudah statement. He's correcting the חכמים's Chachamim statement.
The original text of the משנה mishnah had the חכמים Chachamim saying
רחבה אף על פי שאינה בריאה. rechava af pi she-einah bri'ah. And
he came and he said: No, the חכמים Chachamim say רחבה ובריאה.
rechava u-vri'ah. It's רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehudah that says it's—you don't need
it to be strong, but the חכמים Chachamim need both. So our
current text of the משנה mishnah says תוספות Tosafot incorporates the correction
of רב. Rav. רב Rav edited the text of the משנה mishnah
so now the חכמים Chachamim say what they actually say: wide and
strong. But the original version of it was that the חכמים Chachamim
were saying wide or wide without being strong. Okay, so then according
to תוספות Tosafot again, this is the position of the חכמים. Chachamim.
So now the גמרא Gemara says: ואמר רבי אלעאי אמר רב—one ve-amar
Rebi Ilai amar Rav minute, but רב Rav himself, רבי אלעאי Rebi
Ilai himself says in the name of רב Rav himself: רחבה ארבעה,
rechava arba'ah, it needs to be four wide, אף על פי שאינה
בריאה, af pi she-einah bri'ah, and even if it's not strong enough.
So it seems like רב Rav paskins wide without being strong. So
how is he now changing—I'll read it תוספות's Tosafot way—the text that
the חכמים Chachamim say, the משנה mishnah says wide and strong? So
the גמרא Gemara says: No, רחבה ארבעה שאני. rechava arba'ah shani. If
it's four טפחים tefachim wide, that's different. That's very noticeable, that's significant
in itself. It doesn't have to be strong enough. But if it's
less than four טפחים, tefachim, if it's only one טפח tefach wide,
then it needs to be wide and strong. So again, so according
to תוספות Tosafot what רב Rav did is he clarified that the
חכמים Chachamim disagree with רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehudah and the חכמים Chachamim
say wide and strong, and presumably that is how we rule. Now
we get back to רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehudah. הייתה של קש—if hayetah
shel kash it was made out of straw, you imagine as if
it's made out of metal. מאי קא משמע לן? mai ka mashma
lan? What's this telling us? דאמרינן רואין—you de-amrinan ro'in say we imagine
as if, you know, we imagine as if it's strong enough. If
we imagine straw as if it's metal. This is רבי יהודה Rebbe
Yehudah does not need it to really support. So the גמרא Gemara
says: היינו הך—we hainu hakh just said that! We say it as—according
to רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehudah if it's wide even though it's not
strong. So the גמרא Gemara says: No, מהו דתימא—I mahu de-teima might
have thought דמינה אמרינן—when de-mina amrinan do you say that if it's
the same, if it's the same material? Like if you had a
weak wood you would say, well, you imagine as if it's a
strong wood. שלא במינה לא אמרינן—but she-lo be-mina lo amrinan if it's
not the same material, but if you have straw, to imagine straw
will never be able to support a brick. So to imagine straw
as if it's metal, that's too far-fetched. קא משמע לן ka mashma
lan that we say that. Now again notice that all of this
is because we don't say that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehudah is just
rejecting the criterion. The easier thing for רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehudah would
be to say is: I don't need it to be able to—to,
you know, to support a brick. But if I say no, in
principle I agree with you, it has to support a brick, but
I pretend as if it's made out of a material that is
strong enough.
So if that's true, the גמרא Gemara says, maybe there are limits.
Maybe you don't go from straw to metal if you have to
pretend. And it says no, we're even willing to pretend that way.
Okay, עקומה—now akuma if it's bent, רואין אותה כאילו היא פשוטה—you ro'in
otah ke-ilu hi peshutah look at it as if it's straight. So
the גמרא Gemara says: פשיטא—that's peshita obvious. קא משמע לן כרבי זירא—no,
ka mashma lan ke-Rebi Zeira it teaches us like רבי זירא. Rebi
Zeira. דאמר רבי זירא: de-amar Rebi Zeira: היא בתוך המבוי ועקמומיתה חוץ
למבוי—the hi be-tokh ha-mavoi ve-akmumitah chutz la-mavoi קורה korah is within the
מבוי mavoi but the bend goes outside of the מבוי. mavoi. Here's
your מבוי, mavoi, okay, and the beam goes like this.
Okay, so the actual bend bends outwards and like bows outwards. So
the bend here goes outside of the walls, you know, of the
actual line of the מבוי. mavoi. Okay, so let's see what the
story is. Yes, היא בתוך המבוי Hi betoch hamavoi ועקמומיתה בחוץ למבוי
ve'akmumitah bechutz lamavoi and the bend goes outside of the מבוי. mavoi.
היא בתוך עשרים Hi betoch esrim ועקמומיתה למעלה מעשרים, ve'akmumitah lemalah me'esrim,
let's say if it bows upwards, the beam is within 20 but
the bow goes above the 20 אמה amah line. היא למעלה מעשרה
Hi lemalah me'asarah or it's above ten טפחים tefachim ועקמומיתה למטה מעשרה.
ve'akmumitah lematah me'asarah. The bend goes below the ten טפחים tefachim line.
רואים, Ro'in, you again, you imagine, but now you don't imagine if
it's straight, that would be too easy. But what you imagine is
כל שאילו ינטל עקמומיתה, kol she'ilu yinnatel akmumitah, if you would remove
the bent part, ואין בין זו לזו שלושה, ve'ein bein zo lazo
sheloshah, and there's not three טפחים, tefachim, אין צריך להביא קורה אחרת.
ein tzarich lehavi korah acheret. You don't have to bring another beam.
ואם לאו, ve'im lav, צריך להביא קורה אחרת. tzarich lehavi korah acheret.
And if you do, you do have to bring another beam. So
once in practice you don't need it to actually be able to
accept the beam, you just need sort of the theoretical reality of
a beam that goes across. So what you're allowed to do is
you can erase this. The bend goes into no-man's territory, goes outside
of the legitimate space, right? It either goes outside of the מבוי
mavoi or it goes too high or too low. So fine, that
doesn't care. That part of the beam doesn't count. This part of
the beam does count. If this is
within three, if this is less than three, then it's like the
two parts of the beam that are considered connected. Similarly, if it
went too high, you remove that part and if these are within
three, they are considered connected.
He says רואים כאילו היא פשוטה. Ro'in ke'ilu hi peshutah. Not that
it's as if it has three, then we don't worry about the
part that isn't there. He's saying we see it as if it
is straight.
No, if you're in the משנה. Mishnah. Yeah, the גמרא Gemara is
clarifying though, because it's one thing to say the חכמים Chachamim would
say even this isn't good because this can't, a brick would fall
through, right? This can't receive a brick. He does not require to
receive a brick. He requires it to just be a continuous one
of one טפח. tefach.
Some interpret the משנה Mishnah that the bend is inside the מבוי.
mavoi.
Right, that's a good point. They might interpret the משנה Mishnah that
it bends down or bends up in a way that does not
go into unacceptable territory. Oops. No, basically Dov makes a good point.
This is only a problem if it moves into unacceptable territory.
But don't we already know that if there's a gap, if you
have two beams and they don't quite meet, don't we already know
that?
Yes, but that was my point, which is that the,
oh, you mean why wouldn't the חכמים Chachamim agree to that? Well,
the גמרא Gemara is actually going to say פשיטא Peshita in a
minute. But even besides that, we did find, we did say that
when there's a gap and they don't meet, that's a good point,
there the חכמים Chachamim do say you can say לבוד, lavud, and
even though you can't get a brick in this space, since you
can get a brick on the rest of it, you would. So
why would the חכמים Chachamim disagree with this? I don't know, it's
a good point. Why can't they at least imagine taking something away?
You're not adding something, you're not whatever, you're just saying that part
of it is not acceptable. Maybe they would agree. Maybe they only
don't agree if like the whole thing is, maybe like you said,
maybe in the משנה Mishnah that wasn't the problem. Maybe in the
משנה Mishnah it's not that it went above 20 or below 20,
but it sort of went like this, right? So if you had
something like that, right, then the חכמים Chachamim would say you can't
put a brick anywhere here. And what?
Yeah, I know. But maybe, no, that's maybe he did it out
of straw. So I think Dov makes an excellent point. In the
משנה Mishnah the problem could just be that in practice you can't
put a brick because it's so bent. Here it's dealing with a
different problem, that a section of it is unusable. And you might
be right, it could be the חכמים Chachamim would agree with this.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. הא נמי פשיטא. Ha
nami peshita. The גמרא Gemara says, okay, but that's obvious. If you
remove that part and it's within three, why should it be a
problem? So the גמרא Gemara says, היא בתוך מבוי ועקמומיתה חוץ למבוי
איצטריכא ליה. Hi betoch mavoi ve'akmumitah chutz lamavoi itztericha leh.
Now the one case that's a חידוש chiddush is when part of
the bowing goes outside of the מבוי, mavoi, not too high or
too low, but outside. מהו דתימא, mahu detema, I might have thought,
ליחוש דילמא אתי לאמשוכי בתרה, lichosh dilma ati le'amshuchi batrah, that there
there's a practical problem. You will carry up to where you see
the beam. So if the beam bows outside of the מבוי, mavoi,
you're going to carry, you're going to be looking up at the
מבוי, mavoi, you say, oh, I'm still in a safe zone, I
haven't yet crossed the מבוי, mavoi, and you'll carry outside of the
מבוי. mavoi. So even though technically you've got a good beam, it'll
lead you to carry outside the מבוי. mavoi. קא משמע לן, ka
mashma lan, that teaches us that we're not concerned with that, even
though that seems to be a pretty reasonable concern. But anyway, so
that's what it teaches us. Okay, so now we go on to
the fun part about pi. עגולה רואין אותה כאילו היא מרובעת. Agulah
ro'in otah ke'ilu hi meruba'at.
If something is round, you look at it as if it is
squared off, and as long as it has a טפח tefach diameter.
Again, this is according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah who says that
even if you can't put a brick on it, if you could
cut it in half and it could get a טפח, tefach, a
wide point of a טפח, tefach, that's good enough. הא תו למה
לי? Ha tu lamah li? Why do you need this? It's all
should be obvious. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah just imagines what he needs
to imagine in order to get it to work. So the גמרא
Gemara says, סיפא איצטריכא ליה. seifa itztericha leh. You need it for
the last point. כל שיש בהיקפו ג' טפחים יש בו רוחב טפח.
kol sheyesh behikefo gimel tefachim yesh bo rochav tefach. Anything that has
a three טפחים... tefachim... in circumference has one טפח tefach in diameter,
and it wanted to tell you that geometric fact. Although it's not
fact, but okay. We'll talk about that in a minute. מנא הני
מילי? Mina hani milei? Where do you know this from? אמר רבי
יוחנן אמר קרא,
Amar Rabbi
Yochanan amar k'ra, so says רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, the פסוק pasuk
says, ויעש את הים Vaya'as et hayam by שלמה, Shlomo, he made
this big sort of like מקוה mikvah in the in the בית
המקדש Beit Hamikdash and it was called the ים, yam, an ocean,
but it was a מקוה mikvah in the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash.
So he says he made this מוצק, mutzak, molten, like poured poured
out, you know, metal, עשר באמה, eser ba'amah, ten אמה amah משפתו
אל שפתו misfato el sfato from one edge to the other, so
ten אמות amot in in diameter, עגול, agol, it was circular סביב,
saviv, around, וחמש באמה קומתו, vechamesh ba'amah komato, five אמה amah high,
וקו—and vekov here's the key line—it was ten אמות amot in
diameter, וקו שלשים באמה יסב אתו סביב, vekov shloshim ba'amah yasov oto
saviv, and a line thirty אמה amah long would go around its
circumference. So it says it was thirty אמות amot in circumference and
ten אמה amah wide. So now the גמרא Gemara says, והאיכא שפתו,
Ve'ika sfato, one minute says the גמרא, Gemara, that won't work because
you have the presumably it assumes that the thirty אמה amah circumference
is measured on the inside of the of this מקוה, mikvah, of
this ים, yam, but but the ten אמה amah wide it assumes
go from the outer edges, so it's not it's not accurate because,
you know, because it's
not—the length is longer because it's going to the outer edges. What
about the thickness of the of the edge? So אמר רב פפא,
Amar Rav Pappa, שפתו כשפת כוס פרח שושן כתיב ביה. Sfato kisfat
kos perach shoshan ktiv bei. It says that it was like a
like a petal of a rose petal. It was super thin at
the edges, at certainly at the very tip top of the edge,
and therefore it did not throw off the measurement. דכתיב ועביו טפח,
Dechtiv ve'avyo tefach, the walls were a טפח tefach wide, ושפתו, usfato,
but the edge, the lip, כמעשה כוס kema'aseh kos was like you
make a like a goblet, פרח שושן, perach shoshan, like a, you
know, like a rose petal. אלפיים בת יכיל Alpayim bat yachil and
it contained 2,000 בת. bat. We'll talk about what that is in
a minute. בת Bat is a measurement. So the גמרא Gemara says,
והאיכא משהו. Ve'ika mash'hu. Okay, but it's still throwing it off by
that tiny little thin lip, however much that is. It's still a
משהו. mash'hu. So the גמרא Gemara finally says, okay, כי קחשיב מגואי
קחשיב. Ki kachashiv miguai kachashiv. Fine, so the same way you're measuring
the circumference on the inside, you'll measure the diameter on the inside.
So that deals with that problem. Now תוספות Tosafot raises the issue.
If you look at
תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says,
והאיכא משהו, Ve'ika mash'hu, תוספות Tosafot says, משמע שהחשבון מצומצם. Mashma shehacheshbon
mtzumtzam. It sounds like it's precise. If you care that you're off
by a little bit, it sounds like you really believed that this
is a precise measurement. Why is that a problem? So look at
the at the last line of תוספות, Tosafot, וקשה דאין החשבון מדוקדק
לפי חכמי המידות. Vekasheh de'ein hacheshbon medukdak lefi chachmei hamiddot. According to
those that know geometry, it's not a precise measurement. So if you
said three was a halachic rounding, you know, estimate, by the way
that's what רמב"ם Rambam says in his פירוש המשנה Peirush Hamishnah because
רמב"ם Rambam obviously knew that the geometry was wrong. So רמב"ם Rambam
says, רמב"ם Rambam says that the point of this is to tell
you that for halachic purposes you can round to three for the
definition of pi, which is interesting, which means that it could lead
to a קולא, kula, like, you know, if it has three circumference
you could imagine as if it has one diameter even though it
doesn't have one diameter. But רמב"ם Rambam says that's what we learn
from this. תוספות's Tosafot's problem though is is that—and it sounds like
תוספות Tosafot was willing to accept that this is a rounding
idea—but then he says, and why is the גמרא Gemara bothered about
the tiny little edges if the whole thing is a rounding point
anyway? Okay, so he leaves it with a question. Now what I
have to do is I have to tell you a brilliant גרא.
Gra. The גרא Gra says that the word in the תנ"ך Tanakh
that says the line of the circumference is the word קו. kav.
Okay, the line of the circumference. But he says the כתיב ktiv
of that word, the קרי kri is קו, kav, the כתיב ktiv
is קוה. kavah. Big deal. So he says, what's the גימטריא gematria
of this? This is 106. This is 111. He says if you
take 111 divided by 106 and you multiply it by three, you
have a very close estimate of pi.
So if you do the math—I did this last night—if you do
the math it is, okay, what it is—hold on. Charlie is doing
the math right now.
111 divided by 106 is, whoops, is 1.047
times three
equals—anybody know what pi is? 3.141509.
Pi
is—actual pi is 3.14159.
So that is pi to four significant digits. That's pretty darn interesting.
Okay, now I don't know, so he
basically—the וילנא גאון Vilna Gaon actually did have a secular education?
Yes. The וילנא גאון Vilna Gaon had Euclid's principles translated into Hebrew,
and he thought it was really important that Jews knew math and
geometry.
השלום, Hashalom, the great rabbi— Anyway right
anyway this is a brilliant ווילנא גאון. Vilna Gaon. So I don't
know what the point is. The point is maybe exactly that that
we he's trying to argue that we know Pi more accurately but
we're rounding Pi to three. Again why the גמרא Gemara gets hung
up on the מהו, mahu, which is's question, I don't know the
answer to it. Okay, go ahead.
A friend of mine who's a mathematician actually gave like a whole
דבר תורה dvar Torah exactly on this concept. And what he said
was very interesting is he said the גמרא Gemara had to know
like a better better Pi because it was widely known in many
cultures for a while to a pretty good degree of approximation.
Yeah so so that's what everybody assumes that this has to be
just saying that this is what we use as a rounded number
but again still has a good question.
Yeah so for רמבם Rambam says that for הלכה halacha you go
by this three to one ratio, it's serious like somebody's going to
buy a pool or buy a field, a circular field based...
Yeah you know the question is, yeah it probably would not use
it for בין אדם לחברו bein adam lachaveiro issues. Question about using
it more for like ritual purposes and so on. So like this
type of a thing like if you have a circular סוכה, sukkah,
does it have the right dimensions if you had a square off
and those types of issues. But you're right, for בין אדם לחברו
bein adam lachaveiro issues you'd have to probably be more precise cause
that's the assumption anyway that both parties are working with. Okay so
let's now see as the גמרא Gemara continues. תניא Tanya רבי חייא
Rebbi Chiya so רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya taught a ברייתא. braisa. ים
שעשה שלמה היה מחזיק מאה וחמישים מקוה טהרה. Yam she'asa Shlomo haya
machzik meah v'chamishim mikveh taharah. So it would contain the volume would
be 150 מקואות. mikvaos. Okay now how big is a מקוה? mikveh?
מכדי Michdi let's see. מקוה כמה הוי? Mikveh kama havei? What's a
מקוה? mikveh? ארבעים סאה. Arba'im se'ah. כדתניא ורחץ את בשרו ורחץ את
כל בשרו במים. Ked'tanya verachatz es besaro verachatz es kol besaro bamayim.
You immerse your body in water. במי מקוה Bimei mikveh water of
a מקוה. mikveh. כל בשרו Kol besaro all your flesh. מים שכל
גופו עולה בהן Mayim shekol gufo oleh bahen is that your entire
body could submerge in. וכמה הם? Vechama heim? What is that? אמה
על אמה ברום שלוש אמות. Amah al amah berum shalosh amos. One
אמה amah by one by three אמות. amos. And people are assumed
to be three אמות amos is about four and a half feet.
The גמרא Gemara assumes that three אמות amos gets your shoulders so
it doesn't mean so you would only fit in this type of
a box as it were if you were crouched, not straight standing
up. But be that as it may, three cubic אמות, amos, three
cubic אמות amos is a size of a מקוה. mikveh. ושיעור חכמים
מי מקוה ארבעים סאה Veshiur chachamim mei mikveh arba'im se'ah and that
would be 40 סאה se'ah which is a volume which is a
you know a volume measure, a liquid measure. כמה הוו להו? Kama
havu lehu? So 40 סאה. se'ah. So how much is so now
so and we knew that this מקוה mikveh here it said contained
2,000 בת. bas. We'll find out what 2,000 בת bas is in
a minute. So כמה הוו להו? Kama havu lehu? חמש מאה גרמידי
לתלת מאה מאה. Chamesh meah garmidi letlas meah meah. Now we're going
to do the math. Now here's the thing. Okay so we know
we're going to imagine as if first the מקוה mikveh was the
מקוה mikveh was 10 right by five. That was I'm sorry excuse
me. It was 10 round and by five high. But we're going
to first imagine that it wasn't a circle, it was a square,
cause it makes the math easier. Okay we're going to correct later.
So we're going to imagine rather than it being a circle it
was 10 by 10 by five high. Now if that's true how
what would be the cubic volume of that? 500. Okay now what
we have to do is we have to convert what is the
difference between a the area of a square versus the area of
a circle. So what is the difference? You tell me. Right, we're
imagining it was square but it's really circular. So if this were
if this is let's assume that the radius is one. So the
area of the circle is right pi r squared pi right which
is pi. Right and pi times one squared pi. What is the
area of the square? So the square is two by two right
four. Right. So if pi is three for all intents and purposes,
the ratio of the square to the circle is four to three
or three to four. So if you want to get from the
volume of the square or the area of a square and translate
it to what it would look like in a circle, it would
be 75 percent.
The actual value is 78.5 percent.
It's 78.5 but since pi is three it's 75 percent. So 500
would become anybody want to 375. Okay that is 500 times .75.
Okay so let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. Are we having fun yet? Okay so I am. Okay.
All right so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay so כמה
הוו להו? Kama havu lehu? How big would this מקוה mikveh of
שלמה Shlomo be had it been square? חמש מאה גרמידי Chamesh meah
garmidi 500 cubic אמות. amos. לתלת מאה מאה. Letlas meah meah. So
now we're going to convert that to a
we're going to convert that to how many מקואות mikvaos are there
in 500 cubic אמות. amos. Remember it's three cubic אמות amos per
מקוה. mikveh. So for 300 you'd get מאה meah you'd get 100
cubic
אמות. amos. למאה וחמשין Lemeah v'chamishin 150 you get חמשין chamishin you
get 50. Is that clear what we're doing? We're converting the 500
cubic אמות amos to מקואות. mikvaos. Okay if a
מקוה mikveh is... How much is 500? So 500, so the first
300 becomes, right, becomes 100 מקוות. mikvos. The next 150 becomes 50
מקוות. mikvos. So you'll get 150 מקוות mikvos with less than 500.
How come we said that there were only 150 מקוות mikvos in
this מקוה? mikvah? So it says, let's look at that again. לתלת
מאה מאה, L'tlas meah meah, for the first 300 you get 100
מקוות. mikvos. למאה וחמשין, L'meah v'chamshin, the next 150, חמשין, chamshin, you
get 50 מקוות. mikvos. בארבע מאה וחמשין סגיא, B'arba meah v'chamshin sagya,
450 would be enough to give you 150 מקוות. mikvos. Why did
you say you only have 100, 150? Why did you say you
only have 150 מקוות? mikvos? So the גמרא Gemara says no, הני
מילי בריבועא. hani milei b'ribuya. That would have been if it were
rectangular, right? That's how you got 500. But ים שעשה שלמה, Yam
she'asa Shlomo, but what שלמה Shlomo did wasn't
rectangular. ים שעשה שלמה Yam she'asa Shlomo was עגולה
הוי, agula hava, was circular. So ים שעשה שלמה עגולה הוי. Yam
she'asa Shlomo agula hava. מכדי, Mechdi, let's see. כמה מרובע יתר על
העיגול? Kama meruba yeter al ha'igul? How much is a square bigger
in area than a circle? רביע, Revi'a, a quarter. Like I said,
it's a 4 to 3 ratio, really a 4 to pi ratio,
but the גמרא's Gemara saying a 4 to 3. So if you
deduct from a square, you chop off a quarter, you get the
area of the circle. So לארבע מאה מאה. L'arba meah meah. So
now what we're going to do is if we want to convert
500 into מקוות, mikvos, but we have to reduce a quarter. So
instead of saying 300 equals 100 מקוות, mikvos, right, because three square
cubic whatever per מקוה, mikvah, since we have to reduce by a
quarter, it's going to be 400 equals 100 מקוות mikvos because 400
rectangular equals 300 circular, equals 100 מקוות.
mikvos. Okay, so 400 gets us 100, yes? Okay, so now we've
got 100 מקוות mikvos from the first 400 if it were square.
ולמאה, U'l'meah, the remaining 100, עשרין וחמשא esrin v'chamsha is only going
to get you
25 because 100 if you chop off a quarter becomes 75 for
circular, which becomes 25 מקוות. mikvos. So if you have this ים
של שלמה Yam of Shlomo will only give you 125 מקוות mikvos
and you said 150. So הני
מאה ועשרין וחמשה הוו, hani me'ah v'esrin v'chamsha havu, that's only 125
מקוות, mikvos, you said 150. So the גמרא Gemara says תני רמי
בר יחזקאל ים שעשה שלמה שלשה אמות תחתונות מרובעות ושתים עליונות עגולות.
tani Rami bar Yechezkel Yam she'asa Shlomo shlosha amos tachtonos merubaos v'shtayim
elyonos agulos. No, here's how you get 150. Because the way it
looked was not a total circle. The way it looked was like
this. The first three אמות amos here were square and then afterwards
it became, I don't know, circular on the top. Okay, so therefore
it was a square that became a circle. And that lets us
do our math because this is 3 times 10 times 10, so
the first part contains 300 cubic אמות, amos, which is 100 מקוות.
mikvos. And this here is 10 by 2, so that would have
been, had it been 10 by 10 by 2, it would have
been 200, and then you reduce by a quarter so you get
150. And 150 gives us our other 50 מקוות. mikvos. Okay, so
we get 150 by assuming it was square at the bottom and
circular at the top. Why we're assuming that, not clear. Let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. Yeah, so let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. נהי דאיפכא
לא מצית אמרת. Nehi d'ippcha lo matzit amrat. So the גמרא Gemara
says look, I get why you didn't say the opposite, it was
circular at the bottom and square at the top, דשפתו
ככוס d'sfato k'os kos and it says that the lip of it
was circular. אלא אימא חדא, Ella eima chada, well how do you
get the idea that it was 3 and 2? How do you
get the idea that any part of it was square? Anyway, but
let's say maybe it was 4 and 1, maybe
only
the top אמה ama was circular. לא סלקא
דעתך, Lo salka dach, that doesn't make sense, דכתיב אלפים בת יכיל,
d'chsiv achil bat alpayim, it contained 2,000 בת. bat. Now בת כמה
הוי? bat kama havi? How much is a בת? bat? שלש סאין,
shlosh se'in, three סאה. se'ah. How do you know? דכתיב מעשר הבת
מן הכור, d'chsiv ma'aser habat min hakor, that a בת bat is
a tenth of a כור kor and a כור kor is 30
סאה. se'ah. So a בת bat is 3. So now we have
it contains 2,000 בת bat and a בת bat is 3 סאה.
se'ah. So how many סאה se'ah does it contain?
2,000 בת bat and a בת bat is 3 סאה, se'ah,
6,000. Thank you, was anybody paying attention? 6,000 סאה. se'ah. How big
is a מקוה? mikvah? We were talking about cubic אמות, amos, but
how big is a מקוה mikvah in סאה? se'ah? 40 סאה. se'ah.
So if a מקוה mikvah is 40 סאה se'ah and this contains
6,000 סאה, se'ah, how many מקוות mikvos were there? 40 divided by
6,000, 4 divided by 600, 150. Okay, and that's how we got
150 מקוואות, mikvaot, because we knew this contains 6,000 סאה, se'ah, and
we knew that a מקווה mikvah was 40 סאה, se'ah, so we
know there's 150 מקוואות. mikvaot. Okay. So, now, מעשה דבת עינוכורת דהוו
לה שית אלפי גיבריתא, Maiseh de'Vat Yinochort de'havu leh shit alfei gibrisei,
which is 6,000 סאה, se'ah, and that's why we know it's 150
מקוואות, mikvaot, which means it has to be a square and a
circle in order to get the math. Now the גמרא Gemara says
האי גודשא, hai gudsha,
but that's just the volume though. It doesn't talk about your dimensions.
Okay. How do you know if it's circle or square?
It says it's circular, but circular doesn't get us 150 מקוואות, mikvaot,
so the only way it works is if we assume the bottom
was a square. And you're saying right, maybe the bottom was a
rectangle. All right, I don't know. The גמרא Gemara says והכתיב vehachativ
מחזיק, machzik, but doesn't another פסוק pasuk say מחזיק בתים שלשת אלפים?
machzik batim sheloshet alafim? It contains 3,000 בת, bat, not 2,000 בת.
bat. So גמרא Gemara says ההוא לגודשא. hahu legudsha. That's if you
are doing a dry measure and for the, for the like the
hump, I don't know what you would call a hump. So anyway,
so what it's saying is you've got this circular thing here
that contains 2,000 סאה, se'ah, if you, that's a liquid measure, if
you were to fill it with let's say wheat, the wheat would
sort of, you know, hump over and then with that it would
be 3,000 as a dry measure. Okay, now רש"י Rashi says that's
only something like this which is much, much wider than it is
high. Remember it's ten אמה ammah wide and five high. So if
you've got a very, very wide thing you're going to have much
more in terms of the dry measure hump than if you would
if it were narrower. So גמרא Gemara says אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
אביי Abaye שמע מינה, shema mina, we see from this, האי גודשא
תלתא הוי, hai gudsha tlata havei, that the hump of a dry
measure compared to a liquid measure, if it's, רש"י Rashi says these
dimensions, is a third more. Okay, you go from two to three.
ותנן נמי, Utnan nami, we taught similarly, שידת תיבה ומגדל, shidat teivah
umigdal, כוורת הקש וכוורת הקנה. keveret hakesher keveret hakanah. If you have
these big types of containers like a big box and other you
know or a tower, anyway some huge type of a box or
container, they if they're big enough they do not are not considered
a vessel and don't become טמא. tamei. ובור ספינה האלכסנדרית, Ubore sefinah
ha'alexandrit, or a like a you know a pit, not really a
pit but it's more like a water container for a Alexandrian boat,
which you know they would fill when they went on these long
journeys they'd fill these big containers with water so that they could
have water when they're out at sea. Anyway, these were huge containers.
So אף על פי שיש להם שוליים, af al pi sheyesh lahem
shulayim, although they have bottoms and they're you know they're containers, ואינן
מחזיקות ארבעים סאה בלח, ve'ein machzikot arba'im se'ah belach, if they contain
forty סאה se'ah of liquid measure, שהן כוריים ביבש, shehen korayim beyavesh,
which is two כור, kor, and a כור kor is thirty סאה,
se'ah, which is sixty סאה se'ah of dry measure, טהורים. tehorim. So
this is a general principle that a container that is contains forty
סאה se'ah is not considered a vessel. Okay, which is fine, that
has implications for טומאה וטהרה. tumah vetaharah. But for us the important
point is that it said if it's forty סאה se'ah of liquid
measure which is sixty סאה se'ah of dry measure. So you see
the dry measure is 50 percent more. Now who cares? So רש"י
Rashi says or תוספות Tosafot says like here going back to the
point before, it could be like a practical הלכה halachah if we're
doing business. If I tell you I'm going to sell you this
container of wheat, not flattened but with a mounded container, then based
on this we know how big the mound has to be. I
have to make a mound that fits these types of parameters which
it could some you know could be 50 percent more if it
is as רש"י Rashi says wider than it is you know double
the width as it is as it is the height.
That's a huge mound.
That is a pretty huge mound. Okay, more of this on שבת.
Shabbos. All right, funny I actually thought that we were going to
end early. Early. What?